ILGWU Archives Department Records 5780/111
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU Archives Department Records
1900-1987
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5780/111
4 cubic feet
4 linear ft.
Records (documents).
Contains correspondence, forms, and other files pertaining to the archives' everyday operation, as well as photocopies of materials from the ILGWU records on a variety of topics and local unions, and collected printed material about the ILGWU.
5516350
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Z. Guttendorf, May 28, 2009
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 15, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
The ILGWU Archives were established in New York City in 1973, under the direction of Henoch Mendelsund. Robert Lazar served as archivist. The archives sought to collect union correspondence, meeting minutes, collective bargaining agreements, publications, photographs, audio recordings, film, and memorabilia. In 1987, the ILGWU Archives were transferred to the Kheel Center.
Scope and Contents
The records of the Archives Department include administrative records files relating to the establishment and operation of the unit, subject files containing photocopies of archival material, archival records maintained by the department, and publications.
Administrative records document how the archive was built, operated, and used. They include inventory and accession forms, correspondence with union officials and donors, financial records, and guidelines for the processing and care of archival records. These also include procedures for using the collections, guidelines for donating materials, and signed forms by researchers who accessed the archives. Materials relating to the archives' oral history project are also contained in these administrative files. These oral history audio recordings and transcripts (5780 OH and 5780/110 OHT) are available at the Kheel Center.
Subject files include prominent figures in the union, local unions, and other ILGWU affiliates and contain photocopies of records documenting the work of these individuals and organizations. Among the subject files and archival records are the ILGWU's founding meeting minutes (5780/111, box 1, folder 13), as well as minutes of the ILGWU predecessor union Sanctuary Local Assembly 3038 of the Knights of Labor.
Archival records include union correspondence, accounting ledgers, local union meeting minutes, and other material. The accounting ledgers of the Central States region are among the relatively few records held at the Kheel Center that document the activities of that department. The meeting minutes of Local 89, Local 48, Local 414, and Local 2585/414 fill out gaps in other series. These records from the Archives Department complement those in other series of the ILGWU Records
The Archives Department Publications (5780/121 PUBS) consist of printed material collected by the unit. They include newsletters and newspapers from local unions, collective bargaining agreements, membership censuses, financial and statistical reports, information welfare funds, legal records, and some material related to arbitration. Included in the papers of longtime ILGWU Archivist Robert Lazar (5780/121) is published sheet music.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records 5780/121: ILGWU Archives Department, Robert Lazar Papers 5780/121 PUBS: ILGWU Archives Department Collected Publications
Women's clothing industry -- New York (State) -- New York; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Clothing trade -- New York (State) -- New York; Industrial relations -- New York (State) -- New York; Interrnational Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Archives Dept
5516350
- General Corres. B, 1974-1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Benefits- Union Insurance Plans, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Bialis, Morris, 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- General Correspondence D, 1974-1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- General Correspondence E, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- General Correspondence F, 1974-1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Finance Department, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Forms: Moving- Releases, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Forms: General, 1977-1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Unity Broadcasting Corporation of New England, 1977-1982 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Forms: Accession Sheet (Box 1, Folder 11)
- General Correspondence G, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- General Executive Board: Founding Minutes, 1900-1903 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- General Service Administration, 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Greene, Paula Inc., 1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Scope and Contents
  Spanish
- General Correspondence H, 1977-1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- General Correspondence I, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- International Icrofilmers, Inc., 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Jewish Community Center of Greater Washington, 1975-1983 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Justice, 1973-1982 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- General Correspondence K, 1962-1980 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Oral History Association, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Oral History Projects, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Forms: Access rules and regulations (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Researchers, Names of People Who Used Archives, 1976-1985 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Researchers Signed Access Rules [A], 1978-1986 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Researchers Signed Access Rules [B], 1975-1985 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Researchers Signed Access Rules [C], 1979-1987 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Researchers Signed Access Rules [D], 1979-1983 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Researchers Signed Access Rules [E-F], 1979-1986 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Researchers Signed Access Rules [G], 1979-1987 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Researchers Signed Access Rules [H-J], 1980-1986 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Researchers Signed Access Rules [K], 1978-1985 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Researchers Signed Access Rules [L], 1979-1987 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Researchers Signed Access Rules [M-N], 1979-1986 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Researchers Signed Access Rules [O-P], 1979-1986 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Researchers Signed Access Rules [Q-R], 1979-1984 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Researchers Signed Access Rules [S], 1979-1987 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Researchers Signed Access Rules [T-V], 1980-1987 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Researchers Signed Access Rules [W], 1978-1986 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Researchers Signed Access Rules [X-Z], 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Highsmith and Hollinger, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Cornell University, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Conservation of Archival Material [folder 1 of 2], 1983-1986 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Conservation or Archival Material [folder 2 of 2], 1974-1980 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Demco, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Forms: Archival, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Microfilming, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Studies, Union and Non-Union, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Ledger, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  Oversized, on top of other folders
- CCC, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Shelf List, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- The ILGWU's Archives, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Lazar: Con Edison, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Lecture Series. Holloway, Emory, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Local 60A, 62, 64, 76, 1934-1949 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Oral History Evaluations and Information on Magnetic Tape, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Plotkin General Executive Board Minutes, 1937-1954 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Chicago Convention: Minutes, Articles, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- General Executive Board Minutes. Biography, 1925-1950 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Chicago and Milwaukee 1933-1934; Chicago 1935, 1936, 1933-1936 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Chicago 1937, 1938, 1937-1946 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Stulberg, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Chicago 1939, 1940, 1937-1941 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Milwaukee and Chicago, 1934-1949 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Miami Joint Council, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Chicago Joint Board, 1933-1941 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Kansas City, 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Plotkin: notes, 1935-1947 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- West Coast, 1927-1932 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Dubinsky: Interview, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Interviews: Pending, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Moe Diamond: Interview, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Women in the Union, 1923-1953 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Dressmaker's Union [folder 1 of 2], 1941-1969 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Dressmaker's Union [folder 2 of 2], 1947-1958 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Schindler North East Department, 1936-1959 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- WGWU Local 62: notes, 1935-1968 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Tape Recordings, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Appleton, Shelley, 1954-1967 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Joint Board List (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Chaikin: Notes, 1948-1979 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Chaikin, Sol Chick. President ILG., 1940-1973 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Novik: Notes, 1930-1950 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Pins and Needles, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Archives: Mail, 1980-1984 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Report to Social Security Commission of the Garment Industry, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Joint Board: General, 1983-1986 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- General: A, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- ILGWU, 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Korean; Chinese
- Medical Insurance Plan: ILGWU, 1979-1982 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- General: M, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- General: N, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- General: O, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- General: P, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- General: R, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- General: S, 1976-1981 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- General: T, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- General: U, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- General: W, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Le Java, Mary: Local 134-3043, 1935-1965 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- ALF, CIO: Labor Renewals, 1941-1967 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Bialis: Convention, Notes, 1923-1976 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  1923-1929, 1946, 1959, 1976
- Lewis, Elizabeth: Local 134-3066 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- J. Fogel, 1930-1934 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- ALF-CIO: Printed Material, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Archives: Manual (Box 4, Folder 2)
- C-C, 1983-1987 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- ILGWU Convention, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- D-D, 1984-1986 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Finance: Forms (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Finance: Bills, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Gerber Garment Technology, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Homework, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- T-T, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  Japanese
- Immigration, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- ILGWU: Memos, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Jewish Labor Committee (Box 4, Folder 13)
  List of Persons Rescued
- Oral History, 1973-1986 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- National Board of Coat and Suit Industry, 1974-1977 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Plotkin, Abraham, 1938-1984 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Scarpaci, Jean, 1974-1980 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Society of American Archivists: Labor Archives Committee, 1976-1981 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Schulman, Adolph P., 1947-1976 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  1947, 1974-1976
- Society of American Archivists, 1975-1978 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Society of American Archivists, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Stenzor, Isidor, 1933-1977 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  Yiddish
- T-T, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Robert F. Wagner: Tamiment- New York University, 1975-1985 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- General: U, 1979-1986 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Union Label, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Tamiment/Wagner Library, 1983-1985 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Water Cooler: Great Bear Spring Company, 1984-1986 (Box 4, Folder 28)
- General: V, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Weiss, Shmuel, 1976-1983 (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Yivo Institute, 1975-1985 (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Convention: Opening Fanfare, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 32)
- Slaying the Angel: Women and their Role in the Lowell Experiment, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 33)
- Four: The Union Within the Union, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 34)
- ILGWU, 1976-1986 (Box 4, Folder 35)
- General Executive Board: ILGWU, 1976-1978 (Box 4, Folder 36)
- Imports: Tariffs, 1972-1985 (Box 4, Folder 37)
- Union Literature [folder 1of 2], 1971-1986 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  French
- Union Literature [folder 2 of 2], 1971-1986 (Box 4, Folder 39)
- Text digitized from the collection. (Box 5)